hi there I'm Michaela Peterson Jordan's
daughter just so everyone knows this
podcast was originally posted on my
channel so some of you may have already
seen it dad thought it was a good idea
to post it on his channel as well to
increase viewership and today's also
world benzodiazepine Awareness Day so it
seemed like a good time to post it the
past year was absolutely horrible both
mom and dad almost died repeatedly Andre
my husband and I have spent every day
for the last six months trying to find
my dad help looking everywhere traveling
around the world if it hadn't been for
Andre we wouldn't have made it this was
a difficult interview it flattened both
of us the evening we recorded it he's
been in the public eye for years now and
we both thought explaining what's gone
on in the last year could help other
people avoid the same hell we've been
through we're gonna do another jbp
update in two to three weeks on the
Michaela Peterson podcast to keep people
informed of dads progress and maybe
delve into his future plans please check
out the links in the description and in
the show notes to learn more about the
topics we're about to cover
hi dad
hi kiddo it's really nice to be doing a
family update with you rather than about
you
yeah well it's it feels like a good
thing from this end of the universe as
well good when was the last time you
used a mic to record anything for
YouTube mm-hmm
last fall likely early fall maybe
September it was long maybe yeah almost
a year yeah yeah a long time so I felt
like a long time too it felt like a very
very very long very long time yes well
in the most Canadian fashion I can
muster what the hell happened eh right
that's what people were asking online
name right right what happened well you
know an accident is when three or four
or five unlikely things happen at the
same time and I would say
happened I mean first of all I spent
last January with you in Zurich yeah but
a hospital I wasn't in the hospital but
I was there most of the time you're in
the hospital a lot I was in the hospital
a lot yeah well I had to feed you you
know me or make food for you yeah so I
was there okay
through all of January and you were
getting some pretty invasive surgery
done on your foot and then your mom and
I Tammy and I went to Australia New
Zealand for most of February and that
was actually not too bad a trip I felt
all right and she was feeling all right
- but we knew her surgery for what was
hypothetically a relatively treatable
cancer was coming up in March so that
was hanging over our heads
although we weren't overwhelmingly
worried about it and then she went and
had her surgery and
they then we were informed six weeks
after that after she had recovered but
was still suffering some pain that the
easily treatable and non dangerous slow
growing malignancy that we were told she
had was in fact something fast growing
with about with a some something near a
hundred percent fatality rate within a
year regardless of treatment mm-hmm like
treating cancer like yeah so that was
deadly we got all we were told that in
about ten minutes and so when we were
just expecting uh well if not a clean
bill of health at least a we represent a
ssin of what we'd already been told
she went in to have more invasive
surgery and hypothetically that work but
it created syrup terrible side effects
and that was the start of a whole other
six months long nightmare of trying to
deal with surgical complications which
we did eventually resolve but not until
mid the middle of August in fact not and
literally not until the day of our 30th
wedding anniversary yeah so that was all
hare-raising and stressful to say the
least
I mean you know I've talked about that
but we seem to have a life-threatening
emergency on Tammy's part for both every
three days for about six months and then
I had my own problem start to develop
really in with any degree of severity in
about April May something like that I
had been taking benzodiazepines since
2016 so why be before we get into there
what why why did you start taking
benzodiazepines well in in over the
Christmas vacation in 2016 you and I and
Julianne and my son and Tammy went out
to Vancouver Island to visit her parents
and siblings and when we were there you
and I and Andre your husband ate
something that
didn't agree with any of us and solve a
very severe reaction to that I'm so
unborn it was logical conclusion but I
was
well it the same we have the same
symptoms I don't know if I was any more
seriously affected than you or not but I
was freezing cold for about a month I
couldn't get warm no matter how much I
wore I couldn't stand up without
fainting I couldn't sleep I don't think
I slept at all for for something on the
in the or on the order of three weeks
yeah people like you went on Joe Rogan
and talked about a sulphite reaction you
had and how you didn't sleep and people
commented that oh it's not possible to
stay awake for that long but if you
actually look into sodium metabisulfite
allergies the symptoms that we
experienced aren't unheard of there are
people it's also impossible to stay
awake voluntarily that long that's not
the same as not being able to sleep
those are very very different things
whatever it's possible that when I was
laying there thinking I wasn't sleeping
that now and then I drifted off and
would wake up and not notice I mean I
can't eliminate that as a possibility
but I can certainly tell you that I
slept little enough so that it was
exceedingly unpleasant it's a very long
time to stay awake and when we went back
to Toronto our family physician
prescribed benzodiazepines which are
often used as a sleeping aid and an
anti-anxiety medication and is something
called zopiclone in moving and I hardly
took the EMA vein at all maybe four or
five times but I took the
benzodiazepine the way that it was
prescribed to twice a day point to five
milligrams and that seemed to bring the
symptoms to a pretty rapid halt which is
also part of the reason I didn't need
the EMA vein and then there are so many
other things going on around me at that
time that I never really thought about
it again you know I thought they were
that it was a relatively harmless drug
and I was taking it in a prescribed
fashion at not too high a dose and
I developed symptoms that I now
recognized were associated with its use
weakness on the my left side and like a
feeling of detachment from people around
me people I loved some decrease in the
ability to experience joy but it wasn't
until much later that I actually
associated with the pince-nez being use
yeah when well when your mom got so sick
my anxiety levels had been climbing up
again yeah that was unbearable I mean
the response I had if you're told your
parent or your wife of almost 30 years
has no chance and is going to be dead in
the next ten months that's what we were
told that surgery doesn't help and that
chemo doesn't help and that this is a
fast-growing cancer and you're screwed
no matter what right what we heard in
one day anxiety went all over North
America to New York and to Houston and
to LA looking for different opinions
before we decided to settle on surgery
but and everyone gave us the same
opinion yes which was that nothing is
going to help but surgery was probably
the best mm-hmm the best low-probability
bet yes so so so I asked my doctor to
increase the benzodiazepine dose but
what seemed to happen as a consequence
of that was that I just got more anxious
like so again in retrospect it seems
like I had a rather uncommon but not
unheard of reaction to benzodiazepines
where increased dose makes anxiety worse
instead of better so then at one point
when things weren't getting better and
Tami was still in the hospital I was
trying to take care of her we had lots
of help I stopped taking them entirely
and tried ketamine which is a treatment
for depression while that neither of
those were very good ideas as it turned
out so
I had to stop taking benzodiazepines
entirely
the ketamine oh yeah yeah then I didn't
go then I stayed off them for something
approximating a week not knowing that
that was a very bad idea and I often
think I should have known these things
because I did a lot of scientific
research when I was a graduate student
on alcoholism and I knew that alcohol
and benzodiazepines and barbiturates
were all the same
chemical class at least in terms of
their effect on neurological effects and
but what I knew about benzodiazepines
was that they were comparatively safe
compared to barbiturates which they
basically replaced but that's much less
true than everybody who's taking them
hopes and they're very widely prescribed
and I don't remember what the
probability of developing a dependency
on them is if you take them for more
than two weeks it's 50% I believe it's
something like 50% yeah if you take them
for two or four weeks
yeah and over four weeks it's much much
higher most people prescribed them stay
on them for life and that could have
something to do with the fact that
they're very difficult to get off of
yeah well it was unbelievably unpleasant
I mean it was unbearably unpleasant and
so
I started stopping started tapering off
when Tammy was in the hospital but I
couldn't push that too fast because
wasn't bearable and what what do you
mean it wasn't well my anxiety levels
went higher than I'd ever than anything
I'd ever experienced and I also
developed this condition called
akathisia and the best way I can
describe that is that it was like being
jabbed with something look with a prod
like a cattle prod something electric or
something sharp non-stop for hours for
all the hours I was awake was absolutely
I couldn't sit or lay down or stop
moving and even if I did get up and move
it wasn't like that made it better I
just couldn't stop doing it it was
horrible
a Kathi's ii is horrible it's a it's
it's well it's like being whipped that's
another way of thinking about it
although I really think I would have you
know this is sounds melodramatic but I
think if I had to pick whipping or arc
áthisá those it would depend on how big
a whip but maybe not what an obvious
choice has five pronged whips yes yeah
cat-o'-nine-tails
that might be worse but it was it was
plenty bad yeah and so and things just
fell apart more and more Tammie
recovered rather miraculously in the
middle of August and but I continued my
sort of downhill spiral and ended up in
a clinic in on the eastern seaboard that
claim they could do a rapid yeah
benzodiazepine detox which was a
complete bloody lie yeah well what we
figured was we didn't realize that there
was this physical dependency until you
stopped to try and do the ketamine and
then we tried tapering and you couldn't
stand it because of the akathisia and so
we thought well let's go get some
professional help
right and well and I went to the clinic
on the understanding that they could do
a multi-day detoxification and treatment
for withdrawal and when I got there what
they told me instead was that they'd
substitute essentially they'd substitute
one benzodiazepine for another which
wasn't the least bit helpful because
clonazepam was already a long-acting
benzodiazepine and they're easier to
wean off than the shorter acting
benzodiazepines and they had nothing to
offer essentially I came out of that
clinic worse than I when I went in
so like significantly worse yes on to
more sedative like drugs in order to
dampen down the akathisia
symptoms rights which wasn't helping
much given the fact that the
benzodiazepines were causing the
akathisia yes yeah so and then I went
back to Toronto that's November Nova
and
things maintain their downhill
trajectory apart from the fact that
Tammy was recovering quite nicely which
of course was great but then I ended up
in the hospital in Toronto and the
hospital I ended up went in was also
worse than useless yes so and I don't
remember this part of it it from
December 15th onward you and Andre your
husband took me out of that hospital and
we went to Russia of all places near
Moscow to try a treatment offered by
clinic there that used they use proper
fall index tour right right proper fall
too as a heavy heavy sedating agent it's
basically made me unconscious for nine
days yeah so you were completely out for
nine days well I also had pneumonia
which I developed apparently in the
hospital in Toronto oh yeah it was quite
quite entertaining the whole the whole
string of events we got questions about
you know why why on earth would you go
to Russia when you could get you know
world-class care in North America and
the reason for that was because we had
tried the Ashton protocol we switching
over to valium we tried the Ashton
protocol and lots of people have success
with that although it sounds horrible
lots of people don't have success with
it yeah i'm i put out a the first family
update we did was when you went to the
first rehab center in the states and
after i put that out and said this is
what's going on I had hundreds if not
thousands of people respond telling me
how horrible benzodiazepine withdrawal
could be how they couldn't work how they
were pacing around their backyards for a
year and they basically said just keep
him alive make sure he psychiatrists
that I spoke with said you know when I
asked him how long the it's easy it was
likely the last they said well it could
be two years and I thought no one could
live like this for two years it's like
you can't live for two years if you're
being constantly prodded with something
excruciatingly ly painful on a
moment-to-moment basis it's just not and
there's no escape there's no relief
that's just not possible wasn't possible
or I sir I mean the reason I did survive
certainly wasn't because I was enjoying
my life
the reason was is that I had family
that I was very attached to and friends
who went
above and beyond the call of duty
helping to care for me but
the experience was
intolerably dreadful and it's so strange
was we're now in Serbia weirdly enough
in Belgrade of all bloody places and
we've been here about two weeks and went
to yet another specialty clinic run by
an anesthesiologist and they modified
the medication that I was taking in
Florida which is where we were last and
I don't know I can't understand it but
virtually all my symptoms have
disappeared I'm still weak if I get up
and walk around I don't have my stamina
but I can think clearly
I feel I'm back to my regular self such
as that is yeah during the mornings and
during the days I can work you know it's
very surprising to me that this happened
so rapidly but it it has and that's why
we're doing this podcast and yeah or
this this this video but and hopefully
the last but Tami is coming she's been I
haven't been with her
for more than a few days since middle of
December and that was partly because I
was in bad shape and she wasn't in good
enough shape to be patient with me she
almost died like every day for six
months like you said and you were in you
were suffering so much that anyone
around you suffered yes because of how
horrible it was to watch it was horrible
so just to back up a bit you went to a
hospital in Toronto and they were going
to make things worse rapidly they
weren't willing because of your
akathisia which was making you crazy
they weren't willing to slow tapered you
down they just wanted to stabilize you
by keeping the benzodiazepines there so
Andre and I found a clinic in Russia
that would actually put you to sleep
using proper Falls so you wouldn't have
to suffer while they took the
benzodiazepines out and doing a detox or
as much Halla least you'd be unconscious
for that period time and doing a detox
on benzodiazepines isn't recommended
you're supposed to do a slow taper but
you're akathisia was so bad that even
staying at the same dose was dangerous
right so we needed to get rid of that so
we spent time in Russia managed to get
it out and it was or well you guys took
a big risk taking me out of the hospital
in Toronto which nobody recommended the
psychiatrist certainly weren't in favor
of it and taking me somewhere as foreign
as Moscow and and then attempting this
what generally unadvised treatment was
all surreal yeah what was terrifying and
when I woke up
so as I said - that was complicated by
the fact that I double I had developed
pneumonia in both lungs but when I woke
up I was first catatonic and then
delirious I can remember the delirium
that lasted a whole day consisted of a
sort of dreamlike hallucination that I
had been kidnapped by you were you were
delirious for nine days nine days yeah
nine days you remember the last last day
yeah I remember that I was kidnapped by
people
oddly enough who lived in Florida and
they were like very rural backwoods
people landlord a tree people root
Florida tree people yeah and that they
were gonna keep the leader of this
little gang who kidnapped me we're gonna
kill me because the leader was going to
kill me because he wanted to impress his
girlfriend and it was a very very vivid
dream that I had while I was awake I
knew I was in the hospital at the same
time I was just one of them and I also
remember that when I first woke up I was
irate because I had been
being secured to the side of the bed
because apparently I was tearing out the
IV tubes that I was connected to because
I didn't want to be in the hospital I
had no idea why I was in the hospital or
where the hospital was or where anybody
I knew was we had to back up a bit again
we had agreed when you were in the
hospital in Toronto like our whole
family had sat down and agreed that the
best option was this rapid detox in
Moscow and you'd been part of that
discussion but when you woke up after
the detox in Russia you couldn't
remember any of that right I remember
being really angry with you when you
first showed up because they were very
limited yes but I didn't know that it
was this oh man it was so awful
it was we ended up in like the outskirts
of Moscow in a clinic for severely ill
people yeah
and it was like Soviet ask guard guarded
so the visiting hours were two hours
from driving how far are they to come
and visit I was like two hours each way
right right and in in in Moscow winter
winter in in rough traffic in bad
weather yeah to visit an ICU that was
full of people who were in very rough
shape including me oh yeah you fit right
in when you first got there and at first
it was like how oh my god we brought
dad to Moscow and destroyed him well
that's what the doctor told you wasn't
it the first said that oh yeah
under I couldn't even like there was one
day that was so bad I couldn't go in and
Andre went in and they said you know why
are you here of all places in Russian
and Andre said there was no one to help
him in the West which there wasn't we
looked everywhere right and we tried to
clinics and talked to multiple
psychiatrists and none of them could
help and she said great you've brought
him here to die
so and that was you know the scary thing
about the hospital you were in in
Toronto is you had pneumonia that wasn't
picked up until we got to Moscow so when
you arrived in Moscow you had a fever
and pneumonia in both lungs and so when
they sedated you I the end to intubated
means we had to intubate you during the
sedation because of the pneumonia so we
weren't getting care anywhere and
getting off of benzodiazepines almost
killed you on the place in Russia
managed to stabilize you what it was
yeah to some degree like I didn't have
easier was much reduced yeah when the
benzos were finally so they um they did
some plasmapheresis as well to get rid
of the benzodiazepines in your blood
because the half-life of benzos are so
long that even when you stop taking
little dates of that particular kind you
get early it takes a really long time
for it to get out of your blood so one
of the things they did when you were
under was plasma frees us to get rid of
all the benzodiazepines so when you woke
up the only good thing that had happened
was you weren't taking benzodiazepines
and you weren't a Cathie's 'ok we're
totally screwed but you weren't a
Cathie's right yes and that that was a
great relief and then we went when we
went to rehab center for a while in
moscow that was less medical and more
physiotherapy yeah oriented and for a
while I couldn't I couldn't type because
I couldn't remember how to put my hands
on the keyboard I couldn't walk up and
down stairs because I couldn't see the
stairs properly I couldn't do up buttons
and one night I got up to use the
washroom and then came back into the my
bedroom and I couldn't remember how to
lay down I tried for about 40 minutes I
couldn't remember the sequence of
actions that would enable me to lay down
so this was probably two or three in the
morning I ended up calling for a nurse
so that the nurse who was a very helpful
person could come in and tell me how to
lay down so that was very strange kind
of cortical blindness so I stayed in
there for what two weeks and then we
went to Florida where we thought it
would be sunny and
easier to recover which might have been
but when I was in Florida the aunt my
anxiety levels were I wasn't a Cathie's
ik most of the time but my anxiety
levels were
unbearably high and net that finally got
so bad that I had family members there
who were taking care of me you were
there of course and Andre but also my
parents my sister some friends Tammy
came for a wild my son came for a while
but it got to the point where it was
obvious that just the care of family
members no matter how well-intentioned a
wouldn't be sufficient and Bea was just
too much to ask of people the
responsibility was too great and so
that's when we you at you and Andre had
been communicating with the Serbian
medical clinic for about six weeks
something like that and they'd been
quite helpful
five months okay well this is partly why
we're doing this together is because I
don't know all the facts at at hand yeah
but they were helpful they were helpful
we Andre managed to get in touch with
this
when it can Belgrade where it's not at
least people who are treating you it's
not run by a psychiatrist it's run by an
anesthesiologist which seems to be how
you need to be treated well it's working
for it seems to be working for me at the
present
anyways and that's the best we've got
and it's pretty good because I felt
better probably I felt better see the
things about the benzodiazepines too
that I didn't really understand until I
began to decrease their use I was very I
beat had become quite isolated from my
family members yeah right it was not
most noticeable I would say in my
relationship with my son but it was like
there was a barrier up between million
people it was noticeable it was
noticeable I thought I thought
attributed that to strange twists and
turns my life had taken in the previous
two or three years because there was no
shortage of strangeness on that front
but and then also I had two strange
muscle weakness that plagued me and I
now realize in retrospect that that was
all a consequence of benzodiazepine use
so using him well this is part of the
reason we're doing this this podcaster
video is well to let people know these
are very widely prescribed drugs and
they are not safe to take for more than
two weeks or a month at the absolute
maximum and if you take them longer than
that and you end up addicted you're
gonna or dependent which means that
you'll suffer withdrawal symptoms on
their cessation you are gonna be one
sorry person some people you know have a
better time of it when they stop their
use than others but enough people have a
terrible time so that it's an absolute
it's a it's a medically-induced epidemic
it's a complete bloody catastrophe here
it's probably worse than the opiate
epidemic and that's really saying
something so and I don't know if I'm out
of it or not you know I mean I'm I have
a hard time believing how much better I
feel that I did two weeks ago it's it's
it doesn't seem plausible so you know
it's possible all the things will just
deteriorate for me again although
I wouldn't I don't feel like that at the
moment I feel like things are put back
together in an important way
fortunately one thing I've been able to
continue doing through all of this as
I'm writing a new book and it's due in
the middle of July and that's going
quite well and I was able to do that
even when I was in these different
clinics hospitalized in all these
different clinics although I don't think
I did any writing in Russia no not till
the very end yeah at the very end you
did before we went to Florida yep you
were editing yeah well I remembered one
other thing we were gonna discuss you
know some people okay first of all I've
had a tremendous amount of support from
family members and friends like really I
mentioned this earlier but it's worth
mentioning again people have gone far
beyond the call of duty to help me and
Tami and I in the last year and a half
and there's been an unbelievably massive
outpouring of public support which has
really taken me by surprise in some
sense because you know it's one thing to
be to express your condolences if you're
discussing someone who like my wife is
suffering from something clearly of her
know of that's clearly not of her making
cancer for example but a dependence is
more ethically questionable right
because you think well everyone thinks
well you know what did the person the
person obviously made some errors in
choice that contributed to this and
that's a reasonable objection but and
despite the fact that
there are many people who
found that their opinions didn't align
with mine let's say the proportion of
negative comments I got about what I was
going through was very small so that was
really something
but nonetheless
one of the things I wanted to talk to
you about today was the fact that what's
the old saying physician heal thyself
right I wrote a self-help book I'm a
psychologist it's like well why the hell
didn't I see this coming and why wasn't
I more cautious and I think those are a
reasonable question why should people
take it well then that's the next
question is why should people take
anything I say seriously because of that
and I guess what I would say is if
you're gonna wait to learn from people
who don't mistake don't make mistakes or
don't have tragedy into their life
you're gonna spend a long time waiting
to learn something and the second thing
I would say is in my lectures and my
writings
I've never suggested that I was anything
other than one of the people who also
needed to learn this lesson these
lessons so I included myself in the
population of people who needed some
moral improvement and
and then the last thing would be
you you have to make that the decision
about whether or not to attend to
anything that I'm doing based on your
own judgement about what I've done and
said and if you find that that's not
convincing then that's your prerogative
than if you find that it's useful then
well I'm delighted by that obviously and
that's that that's as that's as much as
there is to say well I think one of the
points of doing this podcast was to
inform people so that other people don't
have to go through the same thing you
went through because watching it from
the outside
was the worst thing I've ever seen
definitely and
hopefully educating people on the
dangers of this well that's saying
something cuz when you awake when they
replaced your ankle last year in January
oh yeah but that was like there was
still an element of yes I was awake when
they replaced my ankle because I was
trying to avoid the general anesthesia
because I didn't want the general
anesthesia hangover I should have just
done the general anesthesia which is
something I realized when they were
hammering my ankle but yeah watching you
in how long you've been in pain has been
significantly worse and I did want to
mention too because people are going to
be wondering why didn't you again why
you didn't get more help in North
America and one of the reasons was oh we
went to Russia we successfully got dad
off with benzos which to clinics in
North America hadn't been able to do we
did manage to do that
and the damage that the benzos had
caused
and the detox caused was significant but
there wasn't any akathisia so they
brought you back to Florida because we
thought there's no point in leaving you
in a center somewhere right you can come
back you can stay with family and we can
just wait and maybe it's gonna take two
two years it looked like it was gonna
take a really long time if you were ever
going to recover Foley we thought we'll
just it'll be more comfortable in
somewhere like Florida and we waited and
it probably was yeah well Moscow winter
was a little anxiety provoking other
than the medical experience you were
going through it was a little anxiety
provoking so there was Florida and then
the pandemic hit so we didn't we weren't
really able to go anywhere and Andre and
I spent months looking for a place that
would take you and actually treat the
neurological damage done by the
benzodiazepines because this wasn't like
I was when I was 17 and had my ankle and
hip done I took oxycontin a high-level
high dose of oxycontin for a year and
getting off of that I experienced
physical withdrawal no psychological
withdrawal so I'm like lots of people
aren't aware of the difference between
psychological and physical abuse the
difference between abuse and dependence
yeah and physical withdrawals means your
body gets used to the drug that you're
on and when you take it away it's as if
your body is missing something
yeah so with yeah so it's actually
difficult to find it's nearly impossible
to find physicians that know how to
treat neurological damage done by
benzodiazepines it turns out we couldn't
find anyone in North America and we
contacted places because being treated
in North America is would be easier than
being treated in somewhere that the main
language isn't English right and so it
took us five months of negotiations to
find the clinic in Belgrade where there
was an anesthesiologist who could treat
you and thank God that he apparently
knows what he's doing
and then we got here two days after we
were Serbia opened so we weren't waiting
around like twiddling our thumbs trying
to figure out what to do with you we
were actively looking for physicians
that could help you but there weren't
any and we were absolutely terrified
that we'd bring you to a psychiatrist in
North America or a center there and
they'd say his anxiety is through the
roof put him on benzos right and then
that would have been terrible so
we did look everywhere and it's been
very complicated yes that's for sure and
it's been very complicated and so you
know maybe we've well we're confident
enough that we've come out the other
side of it at least to some degree that
we were willing to risk making this
interview this video so yeah you know
the reason we're doing it apart from
telling people that they should be
exceptionally careful with
benzodiazepine prescriptions and like a
very large number of elderly people are
prescribed benzodiazepines most of them
women but plenty of men - and that's you
do that at your peril it also increases
the risk of dementia quite substantially
so that's a lovely additional benefit so
watch it it's it's a
how strophe that benzodiazepines are
being prescribed the way they are so
broadly and so there's that but then
also we felt that because I don't know
how he'd say it because people have been
party to my certain elements of my
private life and me too there's perhaps
that it was morally obligatory to bring
people who were interested up to date on
what's occurred so so far so good you
know it's been nice to see you and Andre
get a break for at least a couple of
weeks and it's been really nice not to
be terrified out of my mind for
I mean in Florida the best I ever got
was not petrified with anxiety but close
to it
yeah I had that for a few days in a row
a couple of times but here
and has a tremor my left hand yeah one
of the things with benzodiazepine
dependence is it increases your seizure
risk after you stop taking them so this
is how serious to give an example about
how serious this physical dependency can
be is for some people even on a low dose
of benzodiazepines if they become
dependent on it and stop they can have
seizures that's how that's how intense
the brain changes can be so you on each
caesar increases the risk of the next
one
you've been at a seizure risk for six
months you're still if you're not on
anticonvulsants so then you have tremors
everywhere and you're a seizure risk
that's ridiculous for six months after
taking after stopping well that's right
because I completely thought it was
interesting too because I was so
appalled by what the benzodiazepines had
done that well I I went from four
milligrams a day to zero last May and
that wasn't tolerable so I went back up
north part of the reason you did that as
people would be like why would you do
that you're supposed to taper first of
all if you don't know about
benzodiazepines it's not obvious that
you have to taper but we you have also
went to a psychiatrist to deal with your
worsening anxiety that you thought was
mainly attributed to mom's cancer and
his suggestion was triquet Amin and
stopped the benzodiazepines so that was
the first psychiatrist we tried yes
right and we went to we saw at least
five of them in different areas before
we got to Russia so it's not like we
didn't give North America a good try
it's just you I mean you ended up you
got worse and worse more psychiatrists
they're generally insisted on doing was
quote treating the underlying problem
unquote when you when the underlying
problem was benzodiazepine withdrawal
not some other issue yeah they didn't
know what to do with benzodiazepine
withdrawal so they tried to treat
something they didn't know what to do
with that didn't exist yeah at least in
all probability didn't exist
yes you got treated by you what you went
to two different clinics and then
multiple other psychiatrists and they
try to treat your underlying problem yes
which we had to have huge arguments
about no this isn't an underlying
there's no underlying problem this is a
benzodiazepine dependency and we need to
get him off of it but he can't tolerate
it because the akathisia so how do you
make him more comfortable while he's
waiting down and there was they had no
idea what to you that's right that's was
something they've been very good at this
clinic yeah and advising you and me for
that matter for the last few months
while I've been trying to yeah my head
screwed on straight again yeah they
tried helping us from afar but we needed
more help than that um so I guess one of
the things we've learned from this is
there may be ways to treat
benzodiazepine withdrawal right that
we're not aware of in North America that
I'm aware of
yes there may be ways we'll talk about
this again at some point in the
relatively near future aspect when we're
more certain that what is happening to
me now is working yeah it's only been
two weeks and like it looks great I'm in
way better shape sense of humors wrong
you can listen to music you're writing
every day yeah and I can I can write I
can create not just edit yeah yeah yeah
it's a real relief to get my my love for
music back and that's like a switch
being turned on because it was gone
completely and now it's back completely
very very strange so yeah so well we
will talk more about what's helped if we
know that it's helped yes um then we
could suggest to people what might be
tried in the absence of any other
options what they can talk to their
doctor but I'd like to reiterate you
know
I don't remember what I think it's one
prescription either in seven or one
prescription in nine in the United
States is either for opiates or
benzodiazepines so that's a huge
obviously a huge proportion of the
prescriptions and there's it's very
probable that someone in your family is
currently taking benzodiazepine or or
will be prescribed them in the future
for long enough to develop a dependence
it's like people need to know this it's
not good those drugs are for short-term
treatment of stress induced anxiety or
for surgery they are used in surgery and
things right yeah but as a long-term
treatment there are complete catastrophe
yeah and not everybody like you know
they'll be the person or two that'll say
well I took them and I got off of you
and that's true
but if you it seems if you look at the
statistics if you're older then it's
harder you you're more likely to form a
dependency right and maybe that's
because your brain isn't as plastic
maybe it takes just longer to heal from
them what's also true of opiates like
not everybody who takes opiates for a
long period of time develops a
pronounced dependence there's lots of
individual variability but the risk is
still extremely high mm-hmm I had people
messaged me after the video and
September is saying they'd gotten off of
multiple drugs and that benzodiazepines
had been the most difficult by far
mm-hmm people with experience with
opiates as well or heroin or something
said benzodiazepines wasn't completely
doable I'd had bouts of depression
before before last fall let's say in my
life and I would have to say those were
among the most among the worst
experiences of my life
but I'd have to say that after searching
long and hard for something that was
worse than depression I finally
discovered it in our Cathie's iya
his Depression was remember we talked
about that right and because you had
suffered boats of depression as well as
the arthritis and one
definition we'd agreed on was that being
depressed was like hearing that your dog
had just died yeah remembering that
continually and that's way yeah you
thought that and there was a dog you
actually like a lot you thought well
that's bad but it's not nearly as bad as
depression not even close right not even
close I thought it was going to be as
bad but then my dog died and I was like
nah depression is way worse sucks the
joy out of absolutely everything
can't even see colors vividly like the
joy out of seeing colors which you don't
even think there's joyous as I did with
that but right cuz well with severe
depression you lose positive emotion and
gain a lot of negative emotion but with
this akathisia it was like all of the
negative emotion associated with
depression plus a very high level of
anxiety plus no positive emotion at all
plus the inability to ever relax even
for a moment and so it was
yeah I wouldn't recommend it yes
watch the hell out for
they're probably not your friend or if
they are they're not your friend for
very long yeah and one of the weird
things I was prescribed lorazepam for
sleep I didn't take it very often
because I found it didn't work very well
thank goodness but the funny thing about
them especially at a low dose is they
don't or they didn't for me anyway
induce any type of euphoria so when you
take an opiate when I took the oxycontin
I didn't like it but there was some sort
of high that had to do with the pain
medication but with the lore as a band
there was just an absence of something
so I think it's probably a sneakier drug
to be on right because I think that's
partly why I didn't notice what it was
doing to me too is that there was no
immediate effect in the day of taking it
I mean I stopped having that terrible
reaction that we attributed to food and
so that eliminated the insomnia and the
anxiety but there was no noticeable
effect from the benzodiazepines and so I
know just never paid any attention to
them and never occurred to me that they
could be causing me serious long-term
damage you'd also take and SSRIs for
over a decade
yes depressant anti-anxiety medication
it turns out turns out those are not the
same medications I even knew that to
some degree because I knew that
SSRIs the antidepressants were much more
effective long-term treatments for panic
disorder than benzodiazepines you know
but
it's quite shocking to me actually that
I didn't know despite my professional
specialty that I had no idea how
catastrophic benzodiazepine use could be
yeah well psychologists don't aren't
psychiatrist psychiatrist prescribed
medication psychologist counsel right
but it's still useful to keep up on the
relevant literature now you know yes
well no I definitely I don't think I'll
forget that yes so you know it's funny
maybe we'll stop with this once I
started to decrease my use of
benzodiazepines I was never tempted to
go back up except right at the beginning
when I went to zero and I had to well
you were gonna have a seizure yeah it
wasn't good
you I couldn't even communicate with you
but I thought after I got out of the
Russian hospital that someone even if
someone put a gun to my head and said
take this yeah I wouldn't well in the
like I think I really think that for me
that it's no overstatement that to say
that for me the consequence of
benzodiazepine withdrawal were worse
than death
so yes that's what it looked like from
the a yes well it it you know you don't
want to say something like that lightly
you know but there were lots of times
plenty of times when
it would have been preferable as far as
I could tell just not to be there than
to experience what I was experiencing
when you when you're in pain people who
are in I mean being at a certain level
of pain is like that right if you're
walking around you know anything over
really like a seven or an eight you
can't stand it yeah so that's what it
looked like from the outside um well the
other thing that that the benzodiazepine
withdrawal did that was absolutely
dreadful bus produce a sense of timing
distortion so this was really obvious
when I first woke up in Russia like the
first day that you and I could speak
again you were wheeling me around in the
aisle of the corridor of the intensive
care unit
we were gonna wheel I was gonna be
wheeled around until it was time for
time to eat and I must have asked you
how many times in ten minutes what time
it was probably every 45 seconds yeah
probably something like that
yeah and that's because for me it felt
like you know what substantial amount of
time had passed an hour or two hours
something like that some terrible amount
of time and so not only was I in pain
and experiencing extremely high levels
of anxiety the duration of time had
extended so that it was really
unbearable it was like the days were
just lasting forever and that's thank
that actually disappeared quite a bit
as the akathisia disappeared and it
isn't the case now thank God but it was
it was brutal
it's funny even now you know because
it's somewhat stressful to have this
conversation
I can feel if I lift up my eyes my
eyebrows a bit like you might when
you're interested in something I can
feel the tremors and tremors in my
forehead and that's partly stress
induced so we should probably stop
talking yeah okay we can call it a day
yes well was good to be able to sit here
and have this conversation we're gonna
go eat a steak that's the theory okay
all right well thank you for talking
with me wow thanks for
thanks for being here it's been a
healthier
thanks for your help do
yeah well I
gonna give up and now we're in Belgrade
and seem to have found an answer thank
God
thanks for listening I've linked
everything we talked about in the
description the rare type of cancer my
mom had sodium metabisulfite allergy
symptoms that caused the original
prescription for benzos papers on
paradoxical reactions to benzos benzo
statistics on dependency information on
akathisia something everyone to be aware
of and other people's experiences with
benzodiazepines what my dad went and is
going through isn't as uncommon as we're
told
benzodiazepine withdrawal can be a life
or death situation if it doesn't make
the people who suffer through it so
miserable they're suicidal they could be
at risk for seizures many people do not
make it my dad was forced to detox
because the akathisia caused by the
benzos was intolerable and we had to
abandon the prescribed tapering approach
after many excruciating months detoxing
from benzos is dangerous it nearly
killed him but the state the
benzodiazepines had put him in was more
dangerous and this isn't too uncommon
most of the celebrity deaths we hear
about are benzo related we're told about
the opiates involved in these cases but
benzos aren't as commonly mentioned
Heath Ledger Amy Winehouse Michael
Jackson Philip Seymour Hoffman Whitney
Houston Tom Petty Anna Nicole Smith all
had benzos related to their deaths when
you look at what happened to these
individuals you might think well that
couldn't happen to me but don't be so
sure we had all the resources we could
have and it took us over a year to
remove the drug and stabilize my dad so
that he could function again and not
feel like he was in hell
he still has neurological damage from
the benzos and it's been six months
since he stopped taking them he's still
at a risk for seizures fortunately we
found world-class physicians who are
treating him properly now it was not
easy to locate these people who would
have guessed they'd be in Serbia we are
going to disclose what's helping my dad
once we're more sure that the treatment
is really working
hopefully this podcast will help other
people avoid the horror my family has
had to experience and is still
experiencing because of benzodiazepines
there are hidden dragons everywhere I'm
just thankful my dad is back
talk to you next week
you